So we talked about the 80/20 approach, but there are other tools we can use
when we think about prioritisation.
And one of the most effective is called the prioritisation matrix.
What is a prioritisation matrix? In this approach, we're thinking about
all the different nodes or endpoints of our tree —
all the issues and analyses we're looking to investigate —
and we're plotting those on a two-by-two matrix, or grid.
And the vertical dimension of this is impact,
and the horizontal dimension is feasibility.
Now, for each of these dimensions, we're not always looking to specifically quantify
exactly what the impact or feasibility is.
In often cases, what we're really trying to get to is:
what's the relative degree of impact? Is it small, medium, large, if you will?
On a feasibility perspective, you might think about
how much time or how many resources this might take to approach.
And when you do this approach, you may want to think about:
if something is high impact and very feasible —
well, that we know we're going to have right at the top of our list of things to do.
If something is low impact and it's very hard to do, that's the bottom of the list.
And things in the other two boxes — if they are high impact but also aren't quite feasible —
that's where the challenge comes.
And you want to think about: are there ways to make it easier to do?
Can you relax some of the constraints
you've perhaps defined in terms of your problem,
in order to get at that? And how confident are you that you need to do that
in order to get to the right solution?
And if things are low impact but they're also very easy to do,
that's where you want to think about:
hey, are there some quick wins you could do early in that problem-solving process,
to actually show progress and help get you to the answer quicker?
Some of the challenges that can arise when using the prioritisation matrix
can typically come from the degree of precision that's involved.
And so if you're thinking about
how confident you need to be in your relative positioning of the impact or the feasibility —
if you're problem solving in the moment,
you might not have a lot of time to define exactly what the inputs to that are
and get to a very precise numerical solution.
But you might be able to say: hey, on a T-shirt sizing —
is it small, medium, large? Or high versus medium versus low?
On a relative basis, how can I come up with a very quick relative placement?
And when you're thinking about a longer-term project, that's typically where
you do want to spend a little more time up front discussing:
well, when we say feasibility, what are the relevant components that drive that?
When we're thinking about impact, can we actually agree,
and do some analysis, to more precisely quantify
what that impact is — so we actually get a good ranked order
of the different priorities.